Register of the Albert Léon Guérard Papers, 1942-1948
Hoover Institution Archives
Albert Léon Guérard Papers,
1942-1948
56019
Guérard, Albert Léon, 1880-1959
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Radio transcripts, memoranda, reports, correspondence, and pamphlets, relating to broadcasts of the French section of the Office of War Information during World War II, and to the activities of the Committee to Frame a World Constitution.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1956.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Committee to Frame a World Constitution.; International organization.; Propaganda, American.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; France.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States. Office of War Information.; Voice of America (Radio program)
Biographical Note
1880, November 3 Born, Paris, France
1899 B.A., University of Paris
1901-1903 Traveling Scholarship in England
1904-1906 Junior Professor of Literature and Examiner in History, Paris Normal School
1906-1907 Instructor, Williams College
1907-1913 Assistant and Associate Professor of French, Stanford University
1913 Author, French Prophets of Yesterday
1913-1924 Professor of French, Rice Institute
1914 Author, French Civilization in the Nineteenth Century
1916 Author, Five Masters of French Romance
1917-1919 Staff, U.S. Army Intelligence and Liaison Services
1920 Author, French Civilization from Its Origins to the Close of the Middle Ages
1923 Author, Reflections on the Napoleonic Legend
1925-1946 Professor of General Literature, Stanford University
1925 Author, Beyond Hatred
1928 Author, Life and Death of an Ideal. France in the Classical Age
1929 Author, L'avenir de Paris
1935 Author, Literature and Society
1936 Author, Art for Art's Sake
1941-1942 Author, The France of Tomorrow
1942-1945 Broadcaster, U.S. Office of War Information
1945 Author, Europe, Free and United
1946 Author, France: A Short History
1948 Author, Personal Equation
1949 Author, Education of A Humanist
1950-1953 Professor of Comparative Literature, Brandies University
1955 Author, Napoleon III
1956 Author, Napoleon I
1957 Author, Fossils and Presences
1959 Author, France, A Modern History
1959, November 13 Died, Stanford, California
Scope and Content of Collection
Radio transcripts, memoranda, reports, correspondence, and pamphlets, relating to broadcasts of the French section of the Office of War Information during World War II, and to the activities of the Committee to Frame a World Constitution.
Container List
- Writings and Transcripts of Radio Broadcasts for the United States Office of War Information (French Section), 1942-1945 (Boxes 1-2)
  Correspondence, notes, a photograph, and transcripts related to Guérard's participation as a writer and a broadcaster for the French Section of the United States Office of War Information (OWI) during World War II, arranged chronologically. Most of the folders contain typescript copies, mimeograph copies, and carbon copies, with author and censor notations, of transcripts of French language broadcasts originating with OWI, 1942-1945. Arrangement of transcripts is chronological by initial broadcast date (when available) of each broadcast series.
  - Project correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Notes and photograph, 1942-1943
  - Transcripts of radio broadcasts, 1942-1945
    - BBC Show Number 1, October 5, 1942
    - "Toulon a balayé les derniers nuages," November 27, 1942
    - "Réflexions d'un américain moyen"
      - "Vice-President Wallace," January 25, 1943
      - "Bombardement sur l'Allemagne," January 29, 1943
      - La Croix-Rouge américaine, January 30, 1943
      - Press review, February 1, 1943
      - "Le Président Roosevelt," February 2, 1943
      - "Winston Churchill en Turquie," February 3, 1943
      - "Stalingrad," February 4, 1943
      - Press review, February 5, 1943
      - Press review, February 7, 1943
      - Regional show for Belgium, February 9, 1943
      - "Les complices ennemis," February 9, 1943
      - "L'Amérique devant les succès russes," February 10, 1943
      - "President Roosevelt's Speech on Lincoln's Birthday: February 12, 1943", February 14, 1943
      - Press review, February 15, 1943
      - Press review, February 16, 1943
      - Press review, February 17, 1943
      - Press review, February 18, 1943
      - Press review, February 21, 1943
      - Press review, February 22, 1943
      - Press review, February 23, 1943
      - Press review, February 24, 1943
      - Press review, February 25, 1943
      - Press review, February 26, 1943
      - Press review, February 27, 1943
      - Press review, March 1, 1943
      - Press review, March 3, 1943
      - Press review, March 4, 1943
      - Press review, March 5, 1943
      - Press review, March 7, 1943
      - Press review, March 8, 1943
      - Press review, March 9, 1943
      - Press review, March 10, 1943
      - Press review, March 11, 1943
      - Press review, March 12, 1943
      - Press review, March 13, 1943
      - Press review, March 15, 1943
      - Press review, March 16, 1943
      - Press review, March 17, 1943
      - Press review, March 18, 1943
      - Press review, March 19, 1943
      - Press review, March 21, 1943
      - Press review, March 22, 1943
      - Press review, March 23, 1943
      - Press review, March 25, 1943
      - Press review, March 26, 1943
      - Press review, March 28, 1943
      - Press review, March 29, 1943
      - Press review, March 30, 1943
      - Press review, March 31, 1943
      - Press review, April 1, 1943
      - Press review, April 2, 1943
      - Press review, April 4, 1943
      - Press review, April 5, 1943
      - Press review, April 6, 1943
      - Press review, April 7, 1943
      - Press review, April 8, 1943
      - Press review, April 9, 1943
      - Press review, April 11, 1943
      - Press review, April 12, 1943
      - Press review, April 13, 1943
      - Press review, April 14, 1943
      - Press review, April 15, 1943
      - Press review, April 16, 1943
      - Press review, April 18, 1943
      - Press review, April 19, 1943
      - Press review, April 20, 1943
      - Press review, April 21, 1943
      - Press review, April 22, 1943
      - Press review, April 23, 1943
      - Press review, April 25, 1943
      - Press review, April 27, 1943
      - Press review, April 28, 1943
      - Press review, April 29, 1943
      - Press review, April 30, 1943
      - Press review, May 1, 1943
      - Press review, May 3, 1943
      - Press review, May 4, 1943
      - Press review, May 5, 1943
      - Press review, May 6, 1943
      - Press review, May 19, 1943
      - Press review, May 20, 1943
      - Press review, May 22, 1943
      - Press review, May 24, 1943
      - Press review, May 25, 1943
      - Press review, May 26, 1943
      - Press review, May 27, 1943
      - Press review (holograph), May 28, 1943
      - Press review, May 28, 1943
      - Press review, May 31, 1943
      - Press review, June 1, 1943
      - Press review, June 2, 1943
      - Press review, June 3, 1943
      - Press review, June 4, 1943
      - Press review, June 5, 1943
      - Press review, June 6, 1943
      - Press review, June 7, 1943
      - Press review, June 8, 1943
      - Press review, June 9, 1943
      - Press review, June 10, 1943
      - Press review, June 11, 1943
      - Press review, June 12, 1943
      - Press review, June 14, 1943
      - Press review, June 15, 1943
      - Press review, June 16, 1943
      - Press review, June 17, 1943
      - Press review, June 18, 1943
      - Press review, June 19, 1943
      - Press review, June 21, 1943
      - Press review, June 22, 1943
      - Press review, June 23, 1943
      - Press review, June 24, 1943
      - Press review, June 25, 1943
      - Press review, June 26, 1943
      - Press review, June 28, 1943
      - Press review, June 29(?), 1943
      - Press review, June 30, 1943
      - Press review, July 2, 1943
      - Press review, July 3, 1943
      - Press review, July 5, 1943
      - Press review, July 6, 1943
      - Press review, July 7, 1943
      - Press review, July 8, 1943
      - Press review, July 9, 1943
      - Press review, July 13, 1943
    - "L'Amérique au jour le jour"
      - Press review, July 22, 1943
      - Press and book review, July 31, 1943
      - Book review, August 4, 1943
      - Book review, August 6, 1943
      - Press review, August 9, 1943
      - Book review, August 10, 1943
      - Book review, August 12, 1943
      - Press review, August 13, 1943
      - Book review, August 18, 1943
      - Book review, August 20, 1943
      - Press review, August 21, 1943
      - Book review, August 26, 1943
      - Book review, August 31, 1943
      - Book review, September 3, 1943
      - Press review, September 7, 1943
      - Press review, September 11, 1943
      - Book review, September 14, 1943
      - Press review, September 15(?), 1943
      - Book review, September 18, 1943
      - Book review, September 21, 1943
      - Book review, September 24, 1943
      - Press review, September 25, 1943
      - Book review, September 28, 1943
      - Book review, September 30, 1943
      - Press review, October 1, 1943
      - Book review, October 5, 1943
      - Book review, October 7, 1943
      - Press review, October 8, 1943
      - Book review, October 19, 1943
      - Book review, October 21, 1943
      - Press review, October 22, 1943
      - Book review, October 27, 1943
      - Book review, October 28, 1943
      - Journal review, October 30, 1943
      - Book review, November 2, 1943
      - Book review, November 4, 1943
      - Press review, November 10, 1943
      - Book review, November 11, 1943
      - Book review, November 16, 1943
      - Book review, November 18, 1943
      - "Le Discours de Gettysburg," November 19, 1943
      - Book review, November 22, 1943
      - Book review, November 25, 1943
      - Book review, November 26, 1943
      - Book review, November 30, 1943
      - Book review, December 2, 1943
      - Press review, December 3, 1943
      - Book review, December 7, 1943
      - Book review, December 9, 1943
      - Book review, December 14, 1943
      - Book review, December 16, 1943
      - Book review, December 17, 1943
    - "Franco-American Friendship" (Box 2)
      - "1917, 'Lafayette, nous voici!' Les américains en France," August 20, 1943
      - "L'Offensive. L'Armistice," August 26, 1943
      - "La France à New York," September 23, 1943
      - Commentary on Franco-American friendship by Julien Green, October 2, 1943
      - Dialogue on Franco-American friendship with Léon Rothier, October 9, 1943
    - "L'Amérique à vol d'oiseau," October, 1943-January, 1944
      - I. "Aperçu géographique," October 16, 1943
      - II. "Aperçu historique," October 23, 1943
      - III. "La Constitution," November 13(?), 1943
      - IV. "Vie politique," November 13(?), 1943
      - V. "Formation du peuple américain: les éléments non-européens," November 9(?), 1943
      - VI. "Formation du peuple américain: l'immigration européenne," November 18, 1943
      - VII. "L'enseignement primaire et secondaire," December 4, 1943
      - VIII. "L'enseignement supérieur," November 26(?), 1943
      - IX. "La religion aux Etats-Unis," December 18, 1943
      - X. "Le travail," December 25, 1943
      - XI. "La littérature (xixème siècle)," January 1, 1944
      - XII. "La politique étrangère aux Etat-Unis," December 12, 1943
    - "L'élément français dans l'histoire des Etats-Unis", November 8, 1943
    - "Voici l'Amérique," 1944-1945
      - I. "En traversant l'Amérique," undated
      - II. Les universités et l'effort de guerre: Stanford," undated
      - III. "L'Alaska," undated
      - IV. "San Francisco en temps de guerre", undated
      - V. "San Francisco (2)," undated
      - VI. "San Francisco (3): la ville chinoise," undated
      - VII. "San Francisco (4): la cité phénix," undated
      - VIII. "Deux vignettes de San Francisco," undated
      - IX. "Los Angeles (1)"
      - X. "Los Angeles (2): la ville centrifuge," undated
      - XI. "Los Angeles (3): centre intellectuel," undated
      - XII. "Walt Disney (1)," undated
      - XIII. "Walt Disney (2)," undated
      - XIV. "Le nord-ouest: l'Orégon et le Washington," undated
      - XV. "Les îles Hawaii (1)," undated
      - XVI. "Les îles Hawaii (2)," undated
      - XVII. "Le Texas," undated
      - XVIII. "Le Texas," undated
      - XIX. "L'Amérique par les livres: littérature et folklore," undated
      - XX. "Meet Dr. Franklin: Voici le docteur Franklin," undated
      - XXI. "Qu'est-ce qu'un américain?," undated
      - XXII. "L'éducation des adultes (James Truslow Adams, Frontiers of American Culture)," undated
      - XXIII. "L'éducation des adultes (2)," undated
      - XXIV. "La révolution technique (Garet Garrett: A Time is Born)," undated
      - XXV. "La démocratie en marche: l'Autorité de la Vallée du Tennessee" by David E. Lilienthal, Chairman, Tennessee Valley Authority, undated
      - XXVI. "La démocratie en marche (2)," undated
      - XXVII. "Le miracle américain (d'après le livre d'André Maurois), undated
      - XXVIII. "Les buts de guerre (d'après Walter Lippman, U.S. War Aims; Sumner Welles, The Time for Decision)" Hugh Gibson, The Road to Foreign Policy; James T. Shotwell, The Great Decision," undated
      - XXIX. "C'est toujours l'homme qui compte: Clyde W. Tombaugh, astronome," undated
      - XXX. "Reconstruction économique du monde (à propos de Bretton Woods: introduction)," undated
      - XXXI. "Reconstruction économique du monde (2)-- Bretton Woods: le fonds de stabilisation des changes," undated
      - XXXII. "Organisation economique du monde: la banque internationale," undated
      - XXXIII. "Retour aux principes," undated
      - XXXIV. "Rentrée dans le néant," undated
      - XXXV. "'Nous, le peuple...'," undated
      - XXXVI. "Au cinéma: les fêtes de la déliverance," September 25, 1944
      - XXXVII. "L'entrevue Stalin-Eric Johnson," October 2, 1944
      - XXXVIII. "Le film Wilson," undated
      - XXXIX. "Le projet de sécurité collective de Dumbarton Oaks," undated
      - XL. "Le projet de sécurité mondiale de Dumbarton Oaks," undated
      - XLI. "L'Amérique reconnaît la volonte du peuple français," undated
      - XLII. "L'armistice de 1918: à la recherche du temps perdu," November, 1944
      - XLIII. "La démocratie en action: les élections générales," undated
      - XLIV. "La France au comité européen de Londres," undated
      - XLV. "De New York à Belfort," undated
      - XLVI. "Le caractère américain, d'après D. W. Brogan," undated
      - XLVII. "La conférence internationale de l'aviation civile," undated
      - XLVIII. "Les fêtes de Noël," undated
      - XLIX. "La politique étrangère des États-Unis," undated
      - L. "La France signe la déclaration des Nations Unies, undated
      - LI. "Le châtiment des traîtres et la modération francaise," undated
      - LII. "Savoir oò l'on va: le rapport annuel du president," undated
      - LIII. "La sécurité internationale et l'emploi des contingents américains," undated
      - LIV. "La Cour Suprême des États-Unis," undated
      - LV. "L'Office International d'Education (Sources: Dean Kefauver, Dr. Harlow Shapley (Harvard), Mr. James Marshal, New York City Board of Education)," undated
      - LVI. "Lincoln et l'idéal américain," undated
      - LVII. "La Conférence de Yalta (Crimée): finir la guerre," undated
      - LVIII. "Georges Washington," undated
      - LIX. "Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes (Sources: Max Lerner, The Mind and Faith of Justice Holmes; Alfred Lief, Representative Opinions of Mr. Justice Holmes; Catherine Bowen, Yankee from Olympus)," undated
      - LX. "La Conférence de Mexico," undated
      - LXI. "L'avenir du Japon (Source: Forum on Japan)," undated
      - LXII. "La Conférence de San Francisco," undated
      - LXIII. "Le Conseil de Sécurité," undated
      - LXIV. "Les declarations de M. Stettinius," undated
      - LXV. "Paris, 1919-San Francisco, 1945," undated
      - LXVI. "La Conférence s'ouvre: perspectives historiques," undated
      - LXVII. "San Francisco: l'atmosphere de la ville," undated
      - LXVIII. "L'organisation (le mecanisme) de la Conference," undated
      - LXIX. "Coup d'oeil historique sur la deuxieme guerre mondiale," undated
      - LXX. "La Conférence et les accords regionaux," undated
      - LXXI. "Thomas Mann et l'idéal américain," undated
      - LXXII. "Le rapport de M. Stettinius," undated
      - LXXIII. "L'administration militaire des allies en Allemagne," undated
      - LXXIV. "'Rien n'est perdu.' L'appèl du General De Gaulle (18 juin 1940)," undated
      - LXXV. "La Charte de San Francisco devant le Senat américain," undated
      - LXXVI. "C'est le premier pas," undated
      - LXXVIIa. "Le Quatorze Juillet," undated
      - LXXVIIb. "Le Quatorze Juillet: 'Liberer pour mieux Unir'," undated
      - LXXVIII. "Le Liberateur Bolivar (1783-1830)," undated
      - LXXIX. "La fête nationale belge (Fête de la Constitution, 21 juillet)," undated
      - LXXX. "La démocratie construit...(Sources: Paul Zucker, New Architeture and City Planning; Lewis Mumford, City Development; Henry S. Churchill, The City is the People; Frank Lloyd Wright, When Democracy Builds," undated
      - LXXXI. "Ephérméridés de la liberté: la Nuit du Quatre Aout," undated
      - LXXXII. "Les accords de San Francisco et de Bretton Woods sont ratifies," undated
      - LXXXIII. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (1). Introduction," undated
      - LXXXIV. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (2). Les universités: le nombre n'est pas un crime," undated
      - LXXXV. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (3). Les universités: la liberté," undated
      - LXXXVI. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (4). Les universités: l'égalité (et la fraternité)," undated
      - LXXXVII. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (5). Le roman américain: 'les primitifs'," undated
      - LXXXVIII. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (6). Le roman américain: ce qui lit John Doe," undated
      - LXXXIX. "La vie intellecutelle aux États-Unis (7). Education générale ou apprentissage professionnel?" undated
      - XC. "La vie intellectuele aux États-Unis (8). Réflexions sur l'energie atomique," undated
      - XCI. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (9). Réflexions sur l'energie atomique (2)," undated
      - XCII. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (10). Les cinq frontiers de la pensée," undated
      - XCIII. "La vie intellectuelle aux États-Unis (11.) L'enseignement de l'histoire nationale," undated
      - (Out of Series). "Paris delivre," August 9, 1944
      - (Out of Series). "L'Allemagne s'écroule,' May 8, 1945
- Correspondence and Documents of the Committee to Frame a World Constitution, 1945-1948 (Boxes 3-5)
  Correspondence, project documents, drafts, memoranda, notes, comments, outlines, remarks, considerations, agenda, indexes, circulars, news clippings, reprints, speeches, and pamphlets related to the activities of the Committee to Frame a World Constitution whose members included Robert M. Hutchins, G. A. Borgese, Mortimer Adler, Stringfellow Barr, Albert Guérard, Harold A. Innis, Erich Kahler, Wilbut G. Katz, Charles H. McIlwain, Robert Redfield, and Rexford G. Tugwell. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent, except for committee circular letters, which are arranged chronologically. Documents are arranged according to the committee's original enumeration. The remainder of the material is arranged according to subject. It should be noted that the text of the completed preliminary draft of the world constitution, a summary report, and an index to committee documents were published as Preliminary Draft of a World Constitution, by the Committee to Frame a World Constitution, Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1948.
  - Project correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 3)
    - Barr, Stringfellow
    - Borgese, E. M.
    - Borgese, G. A.
    - Cady, Elizabeth
    - Committee for World Government
    - Hutchins, Robert M.
    - Isely, Philip
    - Kahler, Erich
    - McKeon, Richard P.
    - Tressider, D. B.
    - Tugwell, Rexford G.
  - Circular letters, 1945-1947
  - Indexes to documents, 1945-1948
  - Documents
    - 1, 3-7, 10-11, 14-15, 17, 20-26, 28-30, 32-39, 42, 45, 48, 58, 62-66, 69-70, 72-75, 76b-84, 86-90
    - 92-93, 95-106, 108-132, 134-144, 146-150 (Box 4)
  - Memoranda, drafts, outlines, and project reports pertaining to the drafting of a world constitution by project members, 1945-1947 (Box 5)
  - World Government
  - Atomic energy
  - Charters and constitutions
    - Charter to the United Nations
    - China's Draft Constitution
    - Constitution (Fundamental Law) of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
    - Constitution of the United States of America
    - Draft Constitution of the United States of Europe